# OMAR ABID

Machine Learning Engineer & Researcher | Computer Vision

linkedIn.com/in/omarabid4/ ® github.com/omarabid59 ® omar-abid.ca
C: +1 647 702 1668 | omar.abid4@gmail.com
Toronto, Ontario

### HIGHLIGHTS & OBJECTIVE

Career Objective: Apply my passion as a Machine Learning Engineer / Data Scientist to solve real-world problems that make a positive impact to others. Some of the industries I am interested in include diagnostic imaging, surgical robots and finance.

Experience	Description
4 years	Designing, building and deploying Machine Learning models
4 years	2D and 3D computer vision algorithms for object detection, tracking and mapping
3 years	Software development, version control, unit testing and CI/CD
4 years	Research methods, statistics, physics, biology, technical writing and teaching

### **EDUCATION**

Year	Degree & Institution
2018	MSc, Computer Science & Engineering. Specialization in Machine Learning and Computer Vision, York University
2014	Honors BSc, Biophysics, York University

SKILLS & KNOWLEDGE		
Languages	C/C++, Python, Java, Bash, MATLAB, JavaScript, SQL	
Machine Learning	Neural Networks, SVMs, kNNs, Logistic Regression, Autoencoders	
Cloud Services	GCP, AWS, Azure	
Frameworks	Tensorflow, PyTorch, scikit-learn, NumPy, Pandas, OpenCV, ROS, PCL, CoreNLP	
Computer Vision	OCR, 2D object detection, segmentation and tracking. 3D object detection with SfM & SLAM	
Modeling	Deep learning, CNNs, LSTM RNNs, supervised and unsupervised classification, Bayesian statistics	

## **EXPERIENCE**

2018 - Present	Machine Learning Engineer at Sylphia Consulting (Toronto, ON)
	Designed and implemented a machine learning pipeline for non-invasively measuring hemoglobin
	levels using computer vision on biomedical images.
	Directed a team of engineers for the successful implementation of the system
2018 – 2019	Data Scientist at Watopedia (DIFC, Dubai, U.A.E)
	Designed and implemented large scale machine learning models to identify security threats in
	the transportation sector [Projects 1 - 3].
	<ul> <li>Deployed software to Google Cloud leading to substantial gains in investment capital</li> </ul>

#### 2016 - 2017Teaching Assistant at York University (Toronto, ON)

Invigilated and graded exams and labs for first to third year undergraduate computer science students. Worked with robotics, mobile app development and software design. Directed the labs and office hours for the following courses:

- Fall 2016 | EECS 1011: Computational Thinking Through Mechatronics
- Winter 2016 | EECS 1570: Introduction to Computing for Psychology
- Winter 2016 | EECS 3311: Software Design
- Summer 2016 | EECS 3301: Programming Language Fundamentals

#### 2015 – 2018 Computer Vision Researcher at York University (Toronto, ON)

Improved the efficiency and eliminated bugs on a proprietary neural network simulator implemented in C++ resulting in a more stable system for experimental research purposes

#### 2013 – 2014 Research Assistant at York University (Toronto, ON)

- Hardware Engineer (10/2013 04/2014): Engineered an electronic circuit for reliable measurement of biological cell electric potentials
- Data Analyst (04/2013 08/2014): Statistical data analysis of EEG of Macaque Monkeys for neural population decoding [Project 4]
- Data Analyst (10/2013 08/2014): Statistical data analysis of human behavioral data to infer differences in learning strategies among patients.

#### 2012 – 2013 Software Developer Associate at York University (Toronto, ON)

Recommended and collaborated on the design and implement software interface and communication systems for York University's Rover Team using C++ and Python.

### SIGNIFICANT PROJECTS

Object Real time object detection and notification of threats (suspicious behaviors and objects of interest) in Security critical environments using Deep Neural Networks. Improved effectiveness of clients by allowing quick searching of surveillance video by object type, color, location or time. [Project 1]

Face recognition pipeline in Python using Tensorflow. Resulted in a state-of-the art system that provided real-time security deployment to company clients. Also engineered an algorithm to add new, previously unseen faces to the SQL database for seamlessly updating identities. [Project 2]

Cloud ML model Machine Learning on the cloud with **Google Cloud Platform** for object detection with **WebRTC**, built in Deployment Python. [See GitHub]

Data processing pipeline or collecting, cleaning and augmenting large datasets. Maintained software packages with git resulting in rapid development of machine learning models. [Project 3]

License Plate
Recognition
Reco

Current-voltage measurement system which could reliably measure biological cells electrical potential for research purposes. [Project 5]

Neural population decoding Analyzed **EEG data** of Macaque monkeys using **MATLAB's Statistics and Machine Learning Toolbox**. An **SVM** model was developed that indicated differences in EEG activations under different task conditions leading to key research insights for future work in the lab. [Project 6]

Visualization Convolutional Neural Network layer visualization in real time with TensorFlow's object detection API. [See GitHub]

Object Tracking Deep Learning based object tracking in real time with TensorFlow's object detection API. [See GitHub]

### **ACTIVITIES**

Kaggle Special prize winner of competition "Human Protein Atlas Image Classification" (2019)

Finalist Selected as a NextAl 2018 finalist – An entrepreneurial program for startups in Al. (2018)

Startups Started Fix My Tech Now – A company providing hardware and software repairs for laptops, computers

and mobile devices. (2014 – 2015)

Nomination MSc Thesis Nominated for Best Thesis Award (2018)

Volunteer Scotiabank Buskerfest for Raising Awareness of Epilepsy (2014), Dog Shelter Volunteer (2018)

# **RELEVANT COURSES**

Master's Level Data Mining, Advanced Topics in Computer Vision, Distributed Computing

Bachelor's Level Multivariate and vector calculus, linear algebra, experimental physics with data analysis, statistics,

Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Software Design, Data Structures

Coursera Data Engineering on Google Cloud Platform, Recommendation Systems with TensorFlow on Google

Specialization Cloud Platform

# **PUBLICATIONS**

2019 Master's Thesis: Cognitive Programs Memory: A framework for integrating control in STAR, York University

Sengupta, R., Abid, O., Bachoo, A., & Tsotsos, J. (2017). Attentional blink as a product of attentional control signals: A computational investigation. Journal of Vision, 17(10), 1197-1197.